A Finding Aid to the Gabrielle de Veaux Clements Papers, 1860-1948, in the Archives of American Art AAA.clemgabr
Archives of American Art
Gabrielle de Veaux Clements papers
1860-1948
AAA.clemgabr
Archives of American Art
1 Linear feet
The papers of painter, etcher, printer, muralist, and art teacher Gabrielle de Veaux Clements measure 1 linear foot and date from 1860 to 1948. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including extensive correspondence from Clements to her mother; writings, including notes and essays on art history and etching techniques; printed material; artwork; eight sketchbooks; and photographs of Clements, her family and friends, and her work.
Clements, Gabrielle de Veaux
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Gabrielle de Veaux Clements papers were donated by Mrs. Harlan Starr, Jr. in 1983.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 4212-4213 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. The arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter, printer, and art teacher Gabrielle de Veaux Clements (1858-1948) lived and worked in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Baltimore, Maryland; and Folly Cove near Gloucester, Massachusetts. She was known for her etchings and her commissioned murals for the cities of Baltimore and Washington, D.C.
Clements was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to physician Richard Clements and his wife, Gabrielle De Vaux. Her interest in art was supported by her family and, at the age of seventeen, she began studying lithography with the designer Charles Page at the Philadelphia School of Design for Women. After graduating in 1880 from Cornell University, where she had produced a number of scientific drawings and lithographs, Clements studied with painter Thomas Eakins at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts and won the school’s Toppan Prize. In 1883, Clements was introduced to etching techniques by the artist Stephen Parrish and began exhibiting and printing her works professionally.
In 1884, Clements traveled abroad to Paris to study at the Academie Julian where she was joined in 1885 by fellow painter and future lifelong companion Ellen Day Hale. Upon returning to her Philadelphia studio in 1885, Clements taught other female artists, including Margaret Bush-Brown, and exhibited in numerous institutions, including the National Academy of Design and the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. In 1895, Clements moved to Baltimore to teach art at the newly established Bryn Mawr School, where she remained until 1908. During her tenure in Baltimore, she was commissioned by the Bendann Galleries to etch nine views of Baltimore and also painted five church murals in Washington, D.C., which led to subsequent murals in Detroit, Philadelphia, and Chicago.
Clements and Hale frequently traveled abroad, visiting France, Italy, Egypt, Syria, and Palestine, and spent summers at “The Thickets,” the house they purchased in the artists’ colony at Folly Cove. During World War I, they wintered in Charleston, South Carolina where they opened their studios to young female artists and taught innovative etching, painting, and color printmaking techniques. After the war, they again opened their studios in Folly Cove to young artists and continued to teach and experiment with soft-ground etching and aquatints in color. This work was highlighted in special exhibitions at the J.B. Speed Art Museum and the Smithsonian Institution. Clements died in Rockport, Massachusetts in 1948.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, etcher, printer, muralist, and art teacher Gabrielle de Veaux Clements measure 1 linear foot and date from 1860 to 1948. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including extensive correspondence from Clements to her mother; writings, including notes and essays on art history and etching techniques; printed material; artwork; 8 sketchbooks; and photographs of Clements, her family and friends, and her work.
Biographical material consists of an address book, artwork sales and price lists, and autobiographical notes.
Correspondence is primarily with Clements’ family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from Clements to her mother during her college years at Cornell University.
Writings include notes and essays on art history and etching techniques, 2 notebooks of poetry, and a travel diary chronicling a trip to Egypt with Ellen Day Hale.
Printed material includes clippings, exhibition catalogs, a map of the artists’ colony at Rockport, Folly Cove in Massachusetts, and a copy of the book Suggestions for Illuminating by W. Randle Harrison.
Artwork consists of sketches and original etchings by Clements and artwork by others.
There are 8 sketchbooks consisting primarily of cityscapes, landscapes, and figure and portrait studies.
Photographs are of Clements, her family and friends, artists models, and work by Clements and others.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical materials, circa 1920-1944 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1875-1945 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1885-1940 (8 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed material, circa 1860-1948 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1895-1940 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 6: Sketchbooks, circa 1884-1940 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1875-1940 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Cornell University. Students.; Hale, Ellen Day, 1855-1940; Art teachers--Massachusetts; Art--History; Diaries; Egypt -- Description and travel; Etchers--Massachusetts; Etching--Technique; Muralists--Massachusetts; Photographs; Printmakers--United States; Prints; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Women painters--United States
- Biographical Materials, circa 1920-1944; Series 1; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists of an address book, artwork sales and price lists, and autobiographical notes.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Address Book, circa 1930-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artwork Sales and Price Lists, 1929-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autobiographical Notes, circa 1920-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, circa 1875-1945; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is primarily with Clements’ family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from Clements to her mother during her college years at Cornell University, as well as correspondence from the printer and publisher Charles W. Ames. There is also a carbon copy of a 1945 letter from the sculptor Walker Hancock to his father describing the retrieval of art works confiscated by the Nazis.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A-Z Miscellaneous, circa 1885-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ames, Charles W., 1879-1884 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clements, Gabrielle de Veaux, circa 1875-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - de Vaux, Gabrielle (mother), circa 1877-1880 (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, 1912-1927, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Head, Louisa, circa 1875-1885 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hicks, Margaret, circa 1875-1885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - K., Florence, 1881-1884 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Library of Congress, 1929-1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mills, Hattie May, 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Peggy, 1879-1882 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Polly ("Rubbie"), 1879-1884 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Christmas Cards, circa 1895-1925 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Unknown and Illegible, circa 1885-1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Writings, circa 1885-1940; Series 3; 8 Folders Box 1
  Writings include notes and essays on art history and etching techniques, 2 notebooks of poetry by Clements and Ellen Day Hale, and a 1930 travel diary chronicling a trip to Egypt with Ellen Day Hale.
  Materials are arranged by document type and subject matter.
  - Diary, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notebook of Poetry, circa 1886-1940 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - On Art History, circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - On Artworks, circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - On Etching Techniques, circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Poem, "Christmas", circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Writings by Others, circa 1885-1940 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Printed Material, 1860-1948; Series 4; 5 Folders Box 1
  Printed material consists of clippings; exhibition catalogs; a map of the artists’ colony at Rockport, Folly Cove in Massachusetts; a copy of the book Suggestions for Illuminating by W. Randle Harrison; and a postcard of St. Philip’s Church.
  - Book, Suggestions for Illuminating by W. Randle Harrison, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, 1893-1948 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1923, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Map, Rockport, Massachusetts Artist Colony, circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Postcard, circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Artwork, circa 1895-1940; Series 5; 3 Folders Box 1
  Artwork consists of sketches and original etchings by Clements, a copy of Durer’s “St. Jerome in His Study,” and a print, possibly by Lilian Westcott Hale.
  - Sketches and Original Etchings, circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - By Others, Etching, "St. Jerome in His Study", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - By Others, Sketch (possibly by Lilian Wescott Hale), circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Sketchbooks, 1884-1940; Series 6; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  There are 8 sketchbooks consisting of cityscapes, landscapes, figure and portrait studies, animal and nature studies, and mural designs.
  Materials are arranged by subject matter.
  - Sketchbook #1, Cityscapes, Portrait Studies, and Ships, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Sketchbook #2, Cityscape, Figure and Decorative Studies, 1885-1912 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Sketchbook #3, Landscapes, Cityscapes, and Figure Studies, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Sketchbook #4, Landscapes, Cityscapes, and Figure Studies, circa 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sketchbook #5, Landscape and Portrait Studies, circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Sketchbook #6, Mural Designs, circa 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Sketchbook #7, Nature and Figure Studies, circa 1913-1922 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sketchbook #8, Nature, Figure, and Animal Studies, 1919-1935 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Photographs, circa 1875-1940; Series 7; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Photographs are of Clements and her family and friends, including travel snapshots from the Black Oaks neighborhood in Charleston, South Carolina, and travel photographs from Egypt, France, and Italy. The series also includes snapshots of artist models and scenes, photographs of artwork by Clements, and photographs of 45 paintings and sketches by Lilian Wescott Hale.
  - Photographs of Clements, Family, and Friends, circa 1875-1940 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Photographs of Homes and Buildings, circa 1875-1940 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Travel, Charleston, South Carolina, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 48-51)
  - Travel, Egypt, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Travel, France, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Travel, Italy, circa 1922 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Clements, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Females, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Girls, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Males, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Lilian Westcott Hale, Still Lifes, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Reference Photographs of Animals, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Reference Photographs of Buildings, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Reference Photographs of Cityscapes, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Reference Photographs of Fences and Brickwork, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Reference Photographs of Figure Models, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Reference Photographs of Seascapes, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 65)